Guide to the Jean Louis Berlandier Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Henry R. Wagner Berlandier Papers, 1745-1860; Series I
  - Notebook on Mexico and Texas (Box 16)
    - Mier y Teran, Manuel de, Apuntes para la Comision de limites, 1827 October 26 (Box 16)
      Signed: Mexico, M. de M. y Teran.
    - Vargas, Tomas, Lista de las Tropas que Entraron en Accion en Reotitla el dia 15 de Junio, [1817] (Box 16)
  - Walker, Juan Pedro, Diary of expeditions from Monterey into Texas, 1815-1816 (Box 17)
    Manuscript diary of Pedro Walker made in accordance with the commands of Joaquin de Arredondo. Walker traveled from Monterey to Laredo, Carrizo, the Nueces River, Bexar, Revilla (where he fought Indians), and Soto la Marina.
  - Texas surveys manuscripts
    - Berlandier, Voyage a les Parties N.O. du Texas, 1834 November-December (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Account of the expedition of the northwest part of Texas. Includes description of the land, its flora and fauna, and an encounter with the Comanche.The party included Berlandier, Rafael Chovell, and Francisco Ruiz.
    - Mexico, Comision de limites
      - Calculos de Observaciones Hechas desde el 16 de Oct Hasta el 31 de Dicho, 1832 (Box 18, Folder 2)
        Astronomical calculations made by Berlandier and Chovell.
        Phillipps number 15460
      - De San Antonio de Bexar á la Rivera sur del Rio de la Trinidad, 1828 April-June (Box 18, Folder 3)
        Describes Gonzales, colonial infrastructure, and Autin's colony and its attitude toward slavery. Signed by Rafael Chovell and Luis Berlandier.
        Phillipps number 15481
      - Sketched maps: Bahia de Matagorda; Barra de Aransas; La costa desde Matagorda hasta la boca del Rio Bravo del Norte; Bahia de Galveston; Itinerario de Laredo a Bexar, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
        Six maps; includes table of distances.
    - [Mier y Teran, Manuel de], Nota Medico-Statistique de Matamoros, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Ascribed to Teran by Henry R. Wagner.
  - Gayoso de Lemos, Manuel, Sixteen autograph letters, signed, to William Dunbar from New Orleans and Natchez, concerning running the United States-Florida boundary line, 1797-1798 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    Description of letters available in the folder. Dates include: 1797 January 10, March 9 (2 letters), April 9, and December 20; 1798 February 4, March 15, March 31, April 14, April 30, May 12, June 26, August 3, August 21, August 31, and December 11.
- Materials purchased from H. P. Kraus, Inc., 1826-1844; Series II
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Purchased from H. P. Kraus, Inc. on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 1986.
  Series II is arranged in the order in which it was originally cataloged by the library.
  This portion of the collection contains three journals created by Jean Louis Berlandier detailing trips in Matamoros, Tampico, Tamaulipas, and Nuevo Leon from 1826-1844.
  - Berlandier, Journal d'un voyage au Mexique, 1826-1831, undated (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
    Autograph manuscript journal in two volumes detailing Berlandier's 1826-1831 trip to Mexico. Berlandier records the details of his journey and meteorological observations, particularly in Matamoros and elsewhere in Tamaulipas.
    Phillipps numbers 15528 and 15483
  - Berlandier, Excursion dans le Nouveau Leon, 1844 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    Manuscript journal detailing a trip to Nuevo Leon and describing the geography and people of the region.
    Phillipps number 15589
  - Berlandier, Route de Tampico de Tamaulipas a Mexico at sejour dans cette capitale, 1827 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Manuscript journal containing meteorological, geographical, and social observations made on a trip to Tampico, Tamaulipas, Mexico.
    Phillipps number 15503
- Material donated by William S. Reese, [circa 1850?]; Series III
  Gift of William Reese (Yale 1977), 1993.
  Series III contains one autograph manuscript French-Spanish vocabulary.
  - Berlandier, Interpretates Veborum, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    Autograph manuscript French-Spanish vocabulary.
    Phillipps number 22033
- Miscellaneous Berlandier Manuscripts, 1827-1849; Series IV
  Possibly purchased from Henry R. Wagner, 1919.
  Series IV is arranged in the order in which it was originally cataloged by the library.
  This portion of the collection contains assorted manuscripts from Henry R. Wagner concerning metallurgical, astronomical, medical, and historical observations made by Jean Louis Berlandier, Rafael Chovell, and others.
  - Cuaderno No., circa 1830-1833 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    Bound manuscript document with four entries by Rafael Chovell concerning metallurgical and astronomical observations.
  - Yellow Fever, circa 1842-1847 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    Manuscript documents pertaining to Yellow Fever in Tamaulipas and New Orleans. Also includes a newspaper clipping on Yellow Fever in New Orleans from an unidentified publication.
  - Diseases in Matamoros, 1849 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    Four manuscript documents in Spanish and French on the treatment of Cholera and other diseases.
  - Medecine et chirurgie, circa 1827 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    Three manuscript documents concerning health conditions in Matamoros and Tampico.
  - Del libro intitulado noticias sairas [?] de las indias occidentes, su author Juan Diez de la Calle edit. 1646, se sacaron estas noticias, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
    Manuscript document summarizing the voyages of Christopher Columbus, the conquest of Mexico by Cortes, and the introduction of Christianity into New Spain.
  - Documents relating to natural history, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
    Manuscript copies of three documents in Spanish and French, bound together, pertaining to the establishment by the king of a collection of natural history in Madrid in 1776, the gathering of specimens for this collection, the subject of natural history more broadly, and the origin of the Indians.
  - Extracto del descubrimiento del archipielago del Norte que los Russos han dado a Luz en su Calendario Geographico de este año de 1774, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
    Manuscript document concerning the Russian discovery of a northern archipelago and the exploratory activities of other countries in the north.
  - Berlandier documents relating to Mexican cities and populations (Box 20, Folder 9-10)
    Manuscript documents, eight in French and eight in Spanish, probably relating to Berlandier, with notes on Galeana, Tamaulipas, and Matamoros.
  - Documents pertaining to Berlandier, 1827-1849, undated (Box 20, Folder 11)
    Documents in Spanish and French pertaining to Berlandier. Includes several documents relating to medicine and public health; "Poesyas Varias. Sacadas de los mas selectos autores. Para el uso y gusto de Don Jose Vicente Luna"; an autograph letter, signed, to an unidentified "Dear Sir" from J. Erich Bohmann; and typescript fragments of an unidentfied work.